python is an object-oriented programming
language which means that it supports
classes sometimes when you create a
class you will be doing so to organize
and hold structured data for example
instead of using a dictionary like this
we can use a class like this the thing
is that to Define that person class the
code will be longer than when using a
dictionary I know you're not stranger to
this we have all used a neat special
method before it is the method we use to
initialize a class and as you can see is
very repetitive we have to write the
name and last name on the parameters and
then assign them to sales.name and self
that last name but what if I told you
that we don't have to use they need
special method anymore enter data
classes data classes is a module of the
Python standard library that helps us
write less code when working with python
classes using data classes we can go
from this to this
that is much better right just by using
the data class decorator and by
specifying the name and type of your
data python will automatically generate
they need special method for you but
that is not all when you create a class
without using the data class decorator
and you print an instance of that class
you will see something like this in your
console but when you use a data class
you will see something like this on your
console data classes also allow you to
control the way instances are created
with this code we can create a person
using positional arguments or keyword
arguments when using positional
arguments is very easy to forget what
their order is especially if there are
lots of them when our person class grows
using positional arguments will give you
a headache tell me what's easier to read
and understand creating a class using
positional arguments or keyword
arguments to force our class to only be
create created using keyword arguments
all we have to do is add the KW only
parameter to the data class decorator so
now if we try to do this it won't work
only this will work another cool thing
that you can do with data classes is to
freeze them to make them immutable with
this code if we create an instance of
the class we can later modify its
properties if we want to but if you want
to prevent this from happening if you
want your classes to be immutable to be
unmodifiable after they are created all
you have to do is use the Frozen
parameter and after doing that the class
will be frozen immutable so if you try
to do something like this you will get
an error when creating a data class you
can Define default values as well if you
want to specify more advanced default
values and configure them individually
you can use the field function for
example if we wanted to have a record of
the date when the object is created we
could do something like this here we are
using the field function to tell python
that when our person class is
initialized the get time function should
run to get the default value to the
created ad property so when we create a
new class and print it created ad will
be initialized with the output value of
the get time function using field is how
we can specify default values for list
properties and using field we can
specify which values of the data class
should be hidden or shown when we print
the class in the console if we have this
class and we print it we will see all
its Fields but if we want to hide some
properties like created add we just have
to set the parameter wrapper that stands
for representation to false on the field
function and now when we print our class
created at won't be there the last thing
I want to show you about data classes is
the post in need special method
sometimes you have a class that has a
property that is calculated based on
another property like this one for
example where full name should be
calculated using the first name and last
name instead of initializing the class
like this which will be pointless what
we can do is tell python to not expect
full name when the class is being
initialized by using the field function
with the init parameter set to false and
then we will Define a post in need
special method in our class to
initialize the full name property using
first name and last name the post init
special method will be called after the
init special method so you can be sure
that by the time you access full name it
will already have been defined that's it
for this video I hope that you found it
useful and I hope that you start using
data classes in your code if you weren't
using them already if you like this
content and you would like to see more
of it then please consider leaving a
like And subscribe let me know in the
comments what do you think about data
classes did you know about them are you
already using them are you going to use
them I am very curious to know and don't
forget that if you want to learn things
like python JavaScript react react
native go dark flutter among many others
for absolutely free all you have to do
is click the link below to join any of
our many free courses that you can take
right now for absolutely free with me
click on the link below and I will see
you there honors
see you on the next one bye
thank you